Guide to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Films. ALBA.FILM.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Films
1938-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives
ALBA.FILM.001
3.25 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
Collection consists of films, videos, and DVDs on the Spanish Civil War, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and Spanish Republican refugees, including a 1938 documentary short directed by Henri Cartier–Bresson, With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain; footage shot by Harry Randall, member of the Lincoln Brigade itself, in 1937-1938; a 1939 documentary film directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (aka Jean-Paul Dreyfuss) entitled Refuge, about exiled Spanish Republicans in French refugee camps; and an episode from a 1978 television documentary series on the Spanish Civil War.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact NYU Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Existence and Location of Copies
"With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain Film Collection" (FILM 014) at the Tamiment Library, contains essentially the same film as With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain in this collection; a reference DVD of the same in FILM 014 may be screened for reference purposes. Other films and videos in this collection may also contain parts or versions of With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain, but absent a thorough screening it is not possible to know for certain.
Appraisal
In May 2023, 1 VHS tape was deaccessioned due to duplicative content. In July 2025, 1 VHS tape and 1 Digital Betacam tape were deaccessioned due to duplicative content. In October 2025, 1 Digital Betacam tape was deaccessioned due to duplicative content. In December 2025, 1 commercially available 16mm film was deaccessioned.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in three series.
Series I. Films.
Series II. Videotapes.
Series III. DVDs.
Historical Note
The Spanish Civil War (1936 – 1939) was a conflict between the newly-elected left-leaning government of the Spanish Republic and its supporters and the rebellion against the Republic led by General Francisco Franco and supported by Hitler and Mussolini. Thousands of men and women from around the world volunteered to serve as soldiers and medical and support personnel for the Republic, which organized them into International Brigades (including the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, made up of North Americans). Film was one of the weapons used by international organizations supporting the Republic and the Brigades to document the war and to generate support and raise money; after the war they used moving images to aid the Republic's refugees.
The major works in the collection include With the Lincoln Brigade In Spain, directed by Henri Cartier-Bresson; footage shot by in Spain circa 1937-1938, by Harry Randall, head of the Photographic Unit of the Fifteenth International Brigade (which functioned as the photographic arm of the Lincoln Brigade); and Refuge.
With the Lincoln Brigade In Spain is a short documentary film produced by Herbert Kline, directed by still photographer Henri Cartier-Bresson, and shot in 35mm (although distributed in 16 mm) by Cartier-Bresson and movie camera operator Jaques Lemare. It was filmed in 1937 and released in 1938. Shown in union halls, clubs, and other small venues throughout the United States, the documentary was used to raise funds to bring the Brigaders home. Simultaneously, the same production team filmed Return to Life for the American Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain (AMB). Refuge was shot in 1939 to publicize the plight of Spanish Republican refugees in refugee camps in France and show the conditions in these camps. It was produced by Ciné Liberté and the AMB, directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (also known as Jean-Paul Dreyfuss), and edited by Irving Lerner. It includes footage from (and may be a shortened version of) Un peuple attend, another documentary on the same subject shot earlier that year, and also directed by Le Chanois.
Sources:
• Crusells, Magí."REFUGE, a pro-republican documentary from the Spanish Civil War." International Journal of Iberian Studies 19 (2006): 231-239. Accessed July 3, 2012. doi: 10.1386/ijis.19.3.231_3.
• Faber, Sebastiaan. "Images of Displacement -- The Spanish Civil War and the Birth of the Modern Refugee." The Volunteer 16 (2009): 6-9; 17-18. Accessed July 3, 2012. http://www.oberlin.edu/faculty/sfaber/refugee.pdf
• Randall, Harry, interview by Erika Gottfried. April 10, 2002. New York, New York. Harry W. Randall, Jr. Oral History Interview (transcript). Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Vertical Files: Individuals. Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, New York, New York.
• Rosemont, Franklin. "Spanish Revolution of 1936." In The Encyclopedia of the American Left, Second Edition. Eds. Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, and Dan Georgakas. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. 792-793.
• Salas, Juan. "Henri Cartier-Bresson Film Found in ALBA Archive." The Volunteer 17 (2010): 8-9,11. Accessed July 3, 2012. http://www.albavolunteer.org/2010/03/henri-cartier-bresson-footage-%E2%80%A8found-in-alba-archive/
• Sills, Sam. "Abraham Lincoln Brigade." In The Encyclopedia of the American Left, Second Edition. Eds.Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, and Dan Georgakas. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. 2-4.
Custodial History
The materials in this collection were acquired by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA)—a non-profit organization devoted to preserving the memory of the volunteers who fought against fascism and to defend the Spanish Republic during the Spanish Civil War. ALBA first donated a low-resolution VHS tape of a video transfer of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, a member of the Lincoln Brigade, in 1937-1938 (the Library created a screening copy of this VHS); ALBA then donated the balance of the materials to the Tamiment Library in 2009.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain Film (FILM.014)
Harry Randall: Fifteenth International Brigade Films and Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 011)
Scope and Contents
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Films consist of 16mm films, videotapes in various formats, and DVDs collected by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives on the subjects of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the Spanish Civil War. They include film footage shot in Spain circa 1937-1938 by Harry Randall for the Photographic Unit of the Fifteenth International Brigade; an 18-minute 1937 documentary entitled With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain, produced by Herbert Kline, directed by Henri Cartier-Bresson, and shot by Cartier-Bresson and Jaques Lemare; and Refuge, (1939) a 27-minute documentary film about exiled Spanish Republicans in refugee camps in France that was directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (aka Jean-Paul Dreyfus), and combines newsreels and original footage (including sequences shot with a hidden camera).
The footage shot by Randall includes soldiers (presumably Abraham Lincoln Brigade members and possibly Spanish soldiers as well) at the front and behind the front lines, marching, training, and relaxing, Spanish peasants planting, and scenes of war-caused destruction. With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain documents Brigade members in Spain, training near the front, waiting to be mobilized, wounded, and at hospitals. It includes close-ups of Brigade members, the nurses who treated them, and local residents Brigaders met while recovering from their wounds, as well as scenes of Madrid during the fall of 1937, and a soccer game in Benicàssim.
Videocassettes.; 16mm; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Sources; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Barcelona (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Refugees.; Television journalists.; Television programs.; Motion pictures.; Documentary films; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Archives; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Le Chanois, Jean-Paul, 1905-1985; Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1908-2004; Randall, Harry W., Jr., 1915-; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV. Photographic Unit; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Dreyfuss, Jean-Paul, 1905-1985; Sevareid, Eric, 1912-1992
- Series I. Films, undated
  - With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reel 1., undated; cuid7568 (Box Shared Tamiment 132, Reel 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    16mm film, 500 ft.
  - With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reels 1 & 2., undated; cuid7570 (Box Shared Tamiment 132, Reel 3)
    16mm film, 900 ft.
  - Refuge, undated; cuid7571 (Box Shared Tamiment 127, Reel ALBA.FILM.001_cuid7571)
    16mm film, 1000 ft.
  - Holographic Lincoln Brigade., undated; cuid7572 (Box Shared Tamiment 127, Reel 1)
    16mm film, 700 ft.
  - Otro Crimen de Franco, undated; cuid7573 (Box Shared Tamiment 127, Reel ALBA.FILM.001_cuid7573)
    16mm film, 450 ft.
  - NYU "With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain" 16mm tinted master positive R. 1 (of 2)., undated; cuid7574 (Box Shared Tamiment 170, 16mm film reels 7)
    16mm film, 400 ft.
  - Tam/Wag With the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, Reel 2., undated; cuid7575 (Box Shared Tamiment 170, 16mm film reels 8)
  - [Unlabeled]., undated; cuid7576 (Box Shared Tamiment 170, 16mm film reels 9)
    16mm film, 100 ft.
  - Unlabeled film fragment, undated; cuid7622 (Box 5)
  - Project 221: "To Go To Meet", undated (Box Shared Tamiment 138)
- Series II. Videotapes, 1938 - 1948
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938", May 29, 2003; cuid7577 (Box 2, Vhs 1)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" [2], May 23, 2003; cuid7579 (Box 2, Vhs 3)
  - Spanish Civil War Harry Randall Footage Circa 37-38 Benicàssim [Transfer], undated; cuid7581 (Box 2, Digital betacam 5: [31142050279523])
  - "The Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain" and "Otro Crimen de Franco", 1937, 1948; cuid7583 (Box 2, Cassette 7: [31142050279564])
    Scope and Contents
    Two films related to the Spanish Civil War, one is a copy of Henri Cartier-Bresson's The Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, and the other a Spanish-language film called Otro Crimen de Franco made by Cuban filmmakers.
    Digibeta, 37 min., Black and White, Silent and Sound
    Note: A film print of Henri Cartier-Bresson's The Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain has been preserved. Preservation elements and digital derivatives are available.
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer & 12fps Harry Randall Film Spain 1937-38 ["Clone"], undated; cuid7584 (Box 2, Digital betacam 8: [31142050279598])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, undated; cuid7585 (Box 2, Betacam sp 9: [31142050279689])
  - "Refuge", 1939; cuid7586 (Box 2, Cassette 10: [31142050279648])
    A video copy of the film Refuge directed by Jean-Paul Le Chanois (credited as Jean-Paul Dreyfus). The film was produced by the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.
    Digibeta, 28 min, Black and White, Sound
    Note: This is a telecine transfer from 16mm film; voiceover in English.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    A 16mm film print of Refuge exists in this collection.
  - "Benicàssim" "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical "Dub Master", undated; cuid7588 (Box 2, Digital betacam 12: [31142050279747])
    Silent; Duration: 20 min
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer, Harry Randall Film Spain 37-38 Master, Oct. 9, 1997; cuid7589 (Box 2, Digital betacam 13: [31142050279663])
  - Spanish Civil War, Feb. 20, 2001; cuid7590 (Box 2, Betacam sp 14: [31142050279705])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer ["Clone"], undated; cuid7591 (Box 2, Digital betacam 15: [31142050279713])
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" ["Clone"], undated; cuid7592 (Box 2, Digital betacam 16: [31142050279697 ])
  - George Sossenko's Trip to Spain, April, 1997; cuid7593 (Box 2, Vhs 17: [31142050279754])
  - VALB Tape, undated; cuid7594 (Box 2, Vhs 18: [31142050279770])
  - The Big Picture #12: The Abraham Lincoln Brigade, undated; cuid7595 (Box 2, Betacam sp 19: [31142050279671])
  - "You Are History, You are Legend" The Legacy of the International Brigades, undated; cuid7596 (Box 2, Vhs 20: [31142050279788])
    Duration: 21 minutes
  - Their Cause Was Liberty Sample Material, November 6, 1992; cuid7597 (Box 2, Vhs 21: [31142050279630])
  - "Spanish Civil War" 16mm Transfer ["Dub"], October 10, 1997; cuid7598 (Box 2, Vhs 22: [31142050279762])
  - In Search of the Lincoln Brigade Demo, 1999; cuid7599 (Box 2, Vhs 23: [31142050279655])
  - "Spanish Civil War" Harry Randall Film Spain 1937-38 Jesse Crawford 16mm Transfer, April 24, 2003; cuid7600 (Box 2, Vhs 24: [31142050279721])
  - [Harry Randall Film - Dub of video dub of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, head of the 15th International Brigade's Photographic Unit, in fall/winter 1937], undated; cuid7601 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Vhs 34)
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" ["Film Transfer"], May 29, 2003; cuid7602 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Digital betacam 25: [31142050279606])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade (sometimes called "Benicàssim"), Spanish Civil War Cuban film 1948 ["Master"], December 16, 1996; cuid7603 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Digital betacam 26: [31142050279531])
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade" "In Spain 1938" ["Clone"], May 29, 2003; cuid7604 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Digital betacam 27: [31142050279614])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish Civil War ["Master"]., December 16, 1996; cuid7605 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Digital betacam 28: [31142050279572])
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade 64th Anniversary Reunion "Master", September 15, 2001; cuid7606 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Digital betacam 29: [31142050279622])
  - Harry Randall Film "Spanish Civil War", undated; cuid7607 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Betacam sp 30: [31142050279556])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade (sometimes called "Benicàssim"), Spanish Civil War Cuban film 1948, November 13, 1998; cuid7608 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Betacam sp 31: [31142050279549])
  - Spanish Civil War Refuge (Audio in English) [DCT, "Film Transfer"]., undated; cuid7609 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Cassette 32: [31142050279804])
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archival Film, Spanish Civil War [DCT, "Film Transfer"]., December 14, 1996; cuid7610 (Box Shared Tamiment 114, Cassette 33: [31142050279796])
  - Harvard/MIT Conference, "The Spanish Civil War: the Aftermath", October 16-18, 1986; cuid7616 (Box 5, Cassette 35-46)
  - Pete Seeger, Abraham Lincoln Brigade event, May 1, 2005; cuid7617
    - Tape 326, cuid45007 (Box 5, Minidv cuid45007)
      Duration: 52 minutes.
    - Tape 327, cuid45008 (Box 5, Minidv cuid45008)
      Duration: 45 minutes.
    - Tape 328, cuid45009 (Box 5, Minidv cuid45009)
      Duration: 11 minutes.
  - Noticiario de Laya Films no. 3, 2007-05-02; cuid7623 (Box 5, Cassette 50)
- Series III. DVDs
  - "Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archival 'Film (MOS)' TRT 24:00.", Jan. 30, 1997; cuid7611 (Dvd 1, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - [Harry Randall Film - DVD dub from VHS dub of 16mm footage shot by Harry Randall, head of the 15th International Brigade's Photographic Unit, in fall/winter 1937], undated; cuid7612 (Box Shared Tamiment 120, Box Shared Tamiment 119)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicàssim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 1]., Jan. 29, 1997; cuid7613 (Dvd 2, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicàssim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 2]., Jan. 29, 1997; cuid7614 (Dvd 3, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Brandeis VHS Dub 'Benicàssim' 'Abraham Lincoln Brigade' 16mm Print Transfer Jesse Crawford Historical 24 & 18 fps TRT: 19:00" [Copy 3]., Jan. 29, 1997; cuid7615 (Dvd 4, Box Tamiment/Wagner Master DVD 4)
  - "Dreams and Nightmares: a Personal Memoir of the Spanish Civil War." A film by Abe Osheroff, 1975; cuid7618 (Box 5, Dvd 5)
  - ALBA: Archive of Activism, 2004; cuid7619 (Box 5, Dvd 6)
  - International Brigades Memorial Trust annual meeting, with Ruth Frow, 2006; cuid7620 (Box 5, Dvd 7)
  - Un pessic de memoria al Priorat ("A Pinch of Priorat Memories"), Produced by No jubilem la memoria, 2006; cuid7621 (Box 5, Dvd 8-9)